<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-reddy-dots-home-network-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DOTS signal Call Home">Denial-of-Service Open Threat
    Signaling (DOTS) Signal and Data Channels Call Home</title>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="McAfee">McAfee, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Embassy Golf Link Business Park</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560071</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>kondtir@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Joshi Harsha" initials="J." surname="Harsha">
      <organization abbrev="McAfee">McAfee, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Embassy Golf Link Business Park</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560071</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>harsha_joshi@mcafee.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>DOTS</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document presents DOTS Call Home service, which enables a DOTS
      agent to initiate a secure connection to a DOTS peer, and to convey the
      attack traffic information from the DOTS peer (acting as a DOTS server).
      The DOTS server in turn uses the attack traffic information to identify
      the compromised devices launching the outgoing DDOS attack and takes
      appropriate mitigation action.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t></t>

      <section anchor="problem" title="The Problem">
        <t>The DOTS signal channel protocol <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref> is used to carry
        information about a network resource or a network (or a part thereof)
        that is under a Distributed Denial of Service (DDoS) attack. Such
        information is sent by a DOTS client to one or multiple DOTS servers
        so that appropriate mitigation actions are undertaken on traffic
        deemed suspicious. Likewise, the DOTS data channel protocol <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-dots-data-channel"></xref> is used to install
        filtering rules that may be instantiated immediately or when an attack
        is encountered. Various use cases are discussed in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-dots-use-cases"></xref>.</t>

        <t>IoT devices are becoming more and more prevalent in home networks,
        and with compute and memory becoming cheaper and cheaper, various
        types of IoT devices are available in the consumer market at
        affordable price. But on the downside, the main threat being most of
        these IoT devices are bought off-the-shelf and most manufacturers
        haven't considered security in the product design. IoT devices
        deployed in home networks can be easily compromised, they do not have
        easy mechanism to upgrade, and IoT manufactures may shut shop and
        discontinue patching vulnerabilities on IoT devices. However, these
        vulnerable and compromised devices will continue be used for a long
        period of time in the home, and the end-user does not know that IoT
        devices in his/her home are compromised. The compromised IoT devices
        are typically used for launching DDoS attacks on the victim while the
        owner/administrator of the home network is not aware about such
        misbehaviors. Similar to other DDoS attack, the victim in this attack
        can be an application server, a host, a router, a firewall, or an
        entire network.</t>

        <t>Nowadays, network devices in a home network offer network security,
        for instance, firewall/IPS service on a home router or gateway to
        protect the devices connected to the home network from external and
        internal attacks. Over the years several techniques have been
        identified to detect DDoS attacks, some of these techniques can be
        used enabled on home network devices but most of them are used in the
        Internet Service Provider (ISP)'s network. The ISP offering DDoS
        mitigation service can detect outgoing DDoS attacks and may receive
        filtering rules from upstream service providers using, for example,
        BGP flowspec <xref target="RFC5575"></xref> to filter, block, or
        rate-limit DDoS attack traffic originating from a home network.</t>

        <t>Some of the DDoS attacks like spoofed RST or FIN packets,
        Slowloris, and TLS re-negotiation are difficult to detect on the home
        network devices without adversely affecting its performance. The
        reason is typically home routers have fast path to boost the
        throughput. For every new TCP/UDP flow, only the first few packets are
        punted through the slow path. Hence, it is not possible to detect
        various DDoS attacks in the slow path, since the attack payload is
        sent to the target server after the flow is switched to fast path.
        Deep packet inspection (DPI) of all the packets of a flow would be
        able to detect some of the attacks. However, a full-fledged DPI to
        detect these type of DDoS attacks is operationally not possible for
        all the devices attached to the home network owing to the memory and
        CPU limitations of the home routers. Further, for certain DDoS attacks
        the ability to distinguish legitimate traffic from attacker traffic on
        a per packet basis is complex. This complexity originates from the
        fact that the packet itself may look "legitimate" and no attack
        signature can be identified. The anomaly can be identified only after
        detailed statistical analysis.</t>

        <t>The ISP on the other hand can detect the DDoS attack originating
        from a home network, but the ISP does not have a mechanism to detect
        which device in the home network is generating the DDoS attack
        traffic. The primary reason being devices in a IPv4 Home network are
        behind NAT. Even in case of a IPv6 Home network, though the ISP can
        identify the infected device in the Home network launching the DDoS
        traffic using its unique IPv6 address, but the infected device can
        easily change the IP address to evade remediation.</t>

        <t>Also, the DDoS mitigation service enabled at the ISP network does
        not know whether some traffic is consented or is a suspicious one;
        this may be exacerbated by the unavailability of some control messages
        used by emerging transport protocol (and which were used to be sent in
        clear in TCP, for example). The lack for a clear consent message and
        its association with packets belong to that flow make impose some
        additional requirement on how suspects packets have to be processed by
        the ISP while increasing the security of its own infrastructure and
        avoid negative reputation of its IP resources if more and more
        machines, known to be source of DDoS, are hosted in its network.</t>

        <t>Existing approaches are still suffering from misusing access
        network resources by abusing devices; the support of means for
        blocking such attacks close to the sources are missing. In particular,
        the DOTS signal/data channel protocols do not discuss cooperative DDoS
        mitigation between the home network and ISP to the suppress the
        outbound DDoS attack traffic originating from the home network.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="The Solution">
        <t>This specification addresses the problems discussed in <xref
        target="problem"></xref> and presents DOTS signal/data channel Call
        Home extension, which enables the DOTS server to initiate a secure
        connection to the DOTS client, and the DOTS client conveys the attack
        traffic information to the DOTS server. The DOTS server uses the DDoS
        attack traffic information to identify the compromised device
        launching the DDoS attack, notifies the network administrator, and
        takes appropriate mitigation action. The mitigation action can be to
        quarantine the compromised device or block its traffic to the attack
        target until the mitigation request is withdrawn.</t>

        <t>Abuse traffic can be filtered at the boundaries of the home network
        or at the ISP network. This document defines means to allow for both
        deployment models.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Notational Conventions and Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref><xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <t>The reader should be familiar with the terms defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="DOTS Signal Channel Call Home">
      <section title="Procedure">
        <t>DOTS signal channel Call Home preserves all but one of the DOTS
        client/server roles in the DOTS protocol stack, as compared to DOTS
        client-initiated DOTS signal channel protocol. The one and only role
        reversal that occurs are at the TCP/TLS and DTLS layers; that is, the
        DOTS server acts as a DTLS client and the DOTS client acts as a DTLS
        server or the DOTS server acts as a TCP/TLS client and the DOTS client
        acts as a TCP/TLS server. The DOTS server initiates TCP/TLS handshake
        or DTLS handshake to the DOTS client.</t>

        <t>For example, a home network element (e.g., home router) co-located
        with a DOTS server (likely, a client-domain DOTS gateway) is the
        TCP/TLS server and DTLS server. However, when calling home, the DOTS
        server initially assumes the role of the TCP/TLS client and DTLS
        client, but the network element's role as a DOTS server remains the
        same. Further, existing certificate chains and mutual authentication
        mechanisms between the DOTS agents are unaffected by Call Home
        function. This Call Home function enables the DOTS server co-located
        with a network element (possibly behind NATs and firewalls) reachable
        by only the intended DOTS client and the DOTS server cannot be
        subjected to DDoS attacks. Other motivations for introducing Call Home
        are discussed in Section 1.1 of <xref target="RFC8071"></xref>.</t>

        <t><xref target="signalch"></xref> illustrates sample Call Home flow
        exchange:</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="signalch"
            title="Signal Channel Call Home Sequence Diagram">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                DOTS                                DOTS 
               Server                              Client
                 |                                    |
                 |         1. (D)TLS connection       |
                 |----------------------------------->|
                 |         2. Mitigation request      |
                 |<-----------------------------------|
                 |                                    |
]]></artwork>
          </figure>This diagram makes the following points:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>If UDP transport is used, the DOTS server begins by initiating
            a DTLS connection to the DOTS client. The DOTS client MUST support
            accepting DTLS connection on the IANA-assigned port defined in
            <xref target="port"></xref>, but MAY be configured to listen to a
            different port. If TCP is used, the DOTS server begins by
            initiating a TCP connection to the DOTS client. The DOTS client
            MUST support accepting TCP connections on the IANA-assigned port
            defined in <xref target="port"></xref>, but MAY be configured to
            listen to a different port. Using this TCP connection, the DOTS
            server initiates an TLS connection to the DOTS client.</t>

            <t>Using this (D)TLS connection, the DOTS client requests,
            withdraws, or retrieves the status of mitigation requests.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="DOTS Signal Channel Extension">
        <section title="Mitigation Request">
          <t>This specification extends the mitigation request defined in
          <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref> to convey the
          attacker source prefixes and source port numbers. The DOTS client in
          the mitigation request conveys the following new parameters in the
          CBOR body of the mitigation request:<list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="source-prefix:">A list of attacker prefixes used to
              attack the target. Prefixes are represented using Classless
              Inter-Domain Routing (CIDR) notation <xref
              target="RFC4632"></xref>. <vspace blankLines="0" />As a
              reminder, the prefix length MUST be less than or equal to 32
              (resp. 128) for IPv4 (resp. IPv6).<vspace blankLines="1" />The
              prefix list MUST NOT include broadcast, loopback, or multicast
              addresses. These addresses are considered as invalid values. In
              addition, the DOTS client MUST validate that attacker prefixes
              are within the scope of the DOTS server's domain.<vspace
              blankLines="1" />This is an optional attribute.</t>

              <t hangText="source-port-range:">A list of port numbers used by
              the attack traffic flows. <vspace blankLines="1" />A port range
              is defined by two bounds, a lower port number (lower-port) and
              an upper port number (upper-port). When only 'lower-port' is
              present, it represents a single port number. <vspace
              blankLines="1" />For TCP, UDP, Stream Control Transmission
              Protocol (SCTP) <xref target="RFC4960"></xref>, or Datagram
              Congestion Control Protocol (DCCP) <xref
              target="RFC4340"></xref>, a range of ports can be, for example,
              0-1023, 1024-65535, or 1024-49151. <vspace blankLines="1" />This
              is an optional attribute.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The 'source-prefix', 'source-port-range', 'target-prefix',
          'target-port-range', and 'target-protocol' parameters are mandatory
          attributes when the attack traffic information is signaled by the
          DOTS client.</t>

          <t>The DOTS server uses the attack traffic information to find the
          pre-NAT source IP address of the compromised device and blocks the
          traffic from the compromised device traffic to the attack target
          until the mitigation request is withdrawn. The DOTS server informs
          the DOTS client that the attack traffic is blocked.</t>

          <t>If the DOTS server is co-located with a home router, it can
          program the packet processor to punt all the traffic from the
          compromised device to the target to slow path. The home router
          inspects the punted slow path traffic to detect and block the
          outgoing DDoS attack traffic or quarantine the device (e.g., using
          MAC level filtering) until it is remediated, and notify the home
          administrator about the compromised device.</t>

          <t>If the DOTS server is co-located with a home router is not able
          to enforce appropriate filtering rules within the local network, the
          DOTS server (acting now as a DOTS client) may use the DOTS data
          channel to request explicit filtering from the peer DOTS agent.</t>

          <t>TBD: Do we also want to convey Attack Name/type or ID (the home
          router may not be capable of detecting new emerging/sophisticated
          attacks) ?</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="YANG" title="DOTS Signal Call Home YANG Module ">
          <section title="Mitigation Request Tree Structure">
            <t>This document augments the "dots-signal-channel" DOTS signal
            YANG module defined in <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref> for signaling the
            attack traffic information. This document defines the YANG module
            "ietf-dots-signal-call-home", which has the following
            structure:<figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[module: ietf-dots-signal-call-home
  augment /ietf-signal:dots-signal:
    +--rw source-prefix*       inet:ip-prefix
    +--rw source-port-range* [lower-port upper-port]
       +--rw lower-port    inet:port-number
       +--rw upper-port    inet:port-number]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Call Home Mitigation Request YANG Module ">
            <t><figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[<CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-dots-signal-call-home@2018-09-28.yang"

module ietf-dots-signal-call-home {
  yang-version 1.1;
  namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-dots-signal-call-home";
  prefix signal-call-home;

  import ietf-inet-types {
    prefix inet;
    reference
      "Section 4 of RFC 6991";
  }
  import ietf-dots-signal-channel {
    prefix ietf-signal;
    reference
      "RFC XXXX: Distributed Denial-of-Service Open Threat
                 Signaling (DOTS) Signal Channel Specification";
  }

  organization
    "IETF DDoS Open Threat Signaling (DOTS) Working Group";
  contact
    "WG Web:   <https://datatracker.ietf.org/wg/dots/>
     WG List:  <mailto:dots@ietf.org>
     
     Editor:  Konda, Tirumaleswar Reddy
              <mailto:TirumaleswarReddy_Konda@McAfee.com>";

     Editor:  Mohamed Boucadair
              <mailto:mohamed.boucadair@orange.com>";
     
  description
    "This module contains YANG definition for the signaling
     messages exchanged between a DOTS client and a DOTS server.
     
     Copyright (c) 2018 IETF Trust and the persons identified as
     authors of the code.  All rights reserved.
     
     Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
     without modification, is permitted pursuant to, and subject
     to the license terms contained in, the Simplified BSD License
     set forth in Section 4.c of the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions
     Relating to IETF Documents
     (http://trustee.ietf.org/license-info).
     
     This version of this YANG module is part of RFC XXXX; see
     the RFC itself for full legal notices.";

  revision 2018-09-28 {
    description
      "Initial revision.";
    reference
      "RFC XXXX: Distributed Denial-of-Service Open Threat
                 Signaling (DOTS) Signal Channel Call Home";
  }

  augment "/ietf-signal:dots-signal" {
    when "message-type='mitigation-scope'";
    description "Attacker source details";

    leaf-list source-prefix {
      type inet:ip-prefix;
      description
        "IPv4 or IPv6 prefix identifying the attacker(s).";
    }
    list source-port-range {
      key "lower-port upper-port";
      description
        "Port range. When only lower-port is
         present, it represents a single port number.";
      leaf lower-port {
        type inet:port-number;
        mandatory true;
        description
          "Lower port number of the port range.";
      }
      leaf upper-port {
        type inet:port-number;
        must ". >= ../lower-port" {
           error-message
             "The upper port number must be greater than
              or equal to lower port number.";
        }
        description
          "Upper port number of the port range.";
      }
    }
  }
}]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="DOTS Data Channel Call Home">
      <t></t>

      <section title="Procedure">
        <t><xref target="dcch"></xref> shows the main steps that may be
        observed when a Call Home service is enabled between too peer DOTS
        agents.</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="dcch"
            title="DOTS Call Home: Data Channel Overview">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  +------------+                       +------------+
  | DOTS agent |                       | DOTS agent |
  +------------+                       +------------+
  role=DOTS client                     role=DOTS server
        |                                    |
        |-(1)--Retrieve DOTS Capabilities--->|
        |                ...                 |
        |-(2)--Subscribe to DOTS Call Home-->|
        |                ...                 |
  role=DOTS server                    role=DOTS client
        |                                    |
        |<---Request Filtering Sources--(3)--|
        |                ...                 |
  (4) Enforce filters locally, or

  role=DOTS client                     role=DOTS server
        |                                    |
        |-(5)--Request Filtering Sources---->|
        |                ...                 |
        |                ...                 |  

]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>At bootstrapping, the first DOTS agent #1, acting as a DOTS client,
        contacts its peer DOTS agent #2 (acting as a DOTS server) as per the
        procedure specified in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-dots-data-channel"></xref>. Then, the DOTS client
        sends a request to retrieve the capabilities of the peer DOTS agent
        #2. If that peer agent supports the Call Home service (<xref
        target="capa"></xref>), the DOTS client sends a request to the peer
        DOTS agent #2 to subscribe to the Call Home service (see <xref
        target="reg"></xref> for further details).</t>

        <t>Once the subscription is validated and put into effect, the DOTS
        agent #2 may act as a DOTS client at any moment if it detects some
        suspicious traffic originating from the client domain #1. In order to
        avoid disrupting the service offered to that domain, DOTS agent #2
        sends a request to DOTS agent #1 by means of <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-dots-data-channel"></xref> to request some filtering
        rules to be enforced at the boundaries of the client domain.</t>

        <t>Upon receipt of that request, the DOTS agent #1 may enforce the
        requested filtering rules, relay the request to an administrator, or
        echo the request back to the DOTS agent #2 as per normal DOTS data
        channel procedure.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="DOTS Data Channel Extension">
        <t></t>

        <section anchor="capa" title="DOTS Call Home Capability">
          <t>As specified in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref>, a DOTS client sends a
          GET request to retrieve the filtering capabilities supported by a
          DOTS server. <xref target="cap"></xref> shows an example of such
          request.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="cap"
              title="GET to Retrieve the Capabilities of a DOTS Server">
              <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[  GET /restconf/data/ietf-dots-data-channel:dots-data\
      /capabilities HTTP/1.1
  Host: {host}:{port}
  Accept: application/yang-data+json
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>A DOTS server which supports the Call Home functionality replies
          with a response such as the one depicted in <xref
          target="capex"></xref>.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="capex" title="DOTS Server Capabilities">
              <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[ Content-Type: application/yang-data+json
 {
  "ietf-dots-data-channel:capabilities": {
    "forwarding-actions": ["drop", "accept"],
    "rate-limit": true,
    "transport-protocols": [1, 6, 17, 58],
    "ipv4": {
      "length": true,
      "protocol": true,
      "destination-prefix": true,
      "source-prefix": true,
      "fragment": true
    },
    "ipv6": {
      "length": true,
      "protocol": true,
      "destination-prefix": true,
      "source-prefix": true,
      "fragment": true
    },
    "tcp": {
      "flags-bitmask": true,
      "source-port": true,
      "destination-port": true,
      "port-range": true
    },
    "udp": {
      "length": true,
      "source-port": true,
      "destination-port": true,
      "port-range": true
    },
    "icmp": {
      "type": true,
      "code": true
    }
    "call-home-support": true,
  }
}]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>All the attributes listed in <xref target="capex"></xref> except
          'call-home-support', are defined in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref>. The meaning of
          'call-home-support' parameter is described below:</t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="call-home-support:">This attribute is used by a
              DOTS server to indicate whether it supports the Call Home
              functionality, when set to 'true'.<vspace blankLines="1" />This
              is an optional attribute.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="reg" title="Registration to The Call Home Service">
          <t>In order to make use of DOTS Call Home function, a DOTS client
          MUST register to its DOTS server(s) by creating a DOTS client
          ('dots-client') resource and setting the 'call-home-enable'
          parameter to 'true'. To that aim, DOTS clients send a POST request
          shown in <xref target="register"></xref>.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="register" title="Register to Call Home">
              <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[ POST /restconf/data/ietf-dots-data-channel:dots-data HTTP/1.1
 Host: {host}:{port}
 Content-Type: application/yang-data+json
 {
   "ietf-dots-data-channel:dots-client": [
     {
       "cuid": "string",
       "call-home-enable": boolean
     }
   ]
 }]]></artwork>
            </figure>The 'call-home-enable' parameter is described below:<list
              style="hanging">
              <t hangText="call-home-enable:">If set to 'true', this means the
              DOTS client requests subscribing to the DOTS Call Home service.
              <vspace blankLines="1" />This is an optional attribute.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>A DOTS client can disable its subscription to the Call Home
          service either by de-registering the 'dots-client' resource or by
          sending a registration refresh request with 'call-home-enable' set
          to 'false'.</t>

          <t>A DOTS client which subscribed to a Call Home service should be
          prepared to receive incoming unsolicited requests from the peer DOTS
          agent.</t>

          <t>&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;some text about source port/nat
          traversal&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Tree Structure">
          <t>This document augments the DOTS data channel YANG module defined
          in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-data-channel"></xref> as
          follows:<figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[module: ietf-dots-data-call-home
  augment /ietf-data:dots-data/dots-client:
    +--rw call-home-enable*       boolean
  augment /ietf-data:dots-data/capabilities:
    +--rw call-home-support*      boolean
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </section>

        <section title="YANG Module">
          <t><figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[<CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-dots-data-call-home@2018-09-28.yang"

module ietf-dots-data-call-home {
  yang-version 1.1;
  namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-dots-data-call-home";
  prefix data-call-home;

  import ietf-inet-types {
    prefix inet;
    reference
      "Section 4 of RFC 6991";
  }
  import ietf-dots-data-channel {
    prefix ietf-data;
    reference
      "RFC XXXX: Distributed Denial-of-Service Open Threat
                 Signaling (DOTS) Data Channel Specification";
  }

  organization
    "IETF DDoS Open Threat Signaling (DOTS) Working Group";
  contact
    "WG Web:   <https://datatracker.ietf.org/wg/dots/>
     WG List:  <mailto:dots@ietf.org>
     
     Editor:  Mohamed Boucadair
              <mailto:mohamed.boucadair@orange.com>";

     Editor:  Konda, Tirumaleswar Reddy
              <mailto:TirumaleswarReddy_Konda@McAfee.com>";
     
  description
    "This module contains YANG definition for the signaling
     messages exchanged between a DOTS client and a DOTS server.
     
     Copyright (c) 2018 IETF Trust and the persons identified as
     authors of the code.  All rights reserved.
     
     Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
     without modification, is permitted pursuant to, and subject
     to the license terms contained in, the Simplified BSD License
     set forth in Section 4.c of the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions
     Relating to IETF Documents
     (http://trustee.ietf.org/license-info).
     
     This version of this YANG module is part of RFC XXXX; see
     the RFC itself for full legal notices.";

  revision 2018-09-28 {
    description
      "Initial revision.";
    reference
      "RFC XXXX: Distributed Denial-of-Service Open Threat
                 Signaling (DOTS) Data Channel Call Home";
  }

  augment "/ietf-data:dots-data/ietf-data:capabilities" {
    description 
      "Augments the DOTS data channel with Call Home capability.";

    leaf call-home-support {
      type boolean;
      description
        "DOTS Call Home feature is a capability which is meant 
         to allow a home network to receive requests from the ISP
         network.";
    }
  }

  augment "/ietf-data:dots-data/ietf-data:dots-client" {
    when "/ietf-data:dots-data/ietf-data:capabilities/" +
         "data-call-home:call-home-support='true'";
    description 
      "Allows a DOTS client to enable/disable Call Home 
       functionality.";

    leaf call-home-enable {
      type boolean;
      description
        "When set to 'true', this means the DOTS client registers
         to the Call Home functionality.";
    }
  }
}]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <section anchor="port"
               title="DOTS Signal Channel Call Home UDP and TCP Port Number">
        <t>IANA is requested to assign the port number TBD to the DOTS signal
        channel Call Home protocol for both UDP and TCP from the "Service Name
        and Transport Protocol Port Number Registry" available at:
        https://www.iana.org/assignments/service-names-port-numbers/service-names-port-numbers.xhtml.</t>

        <t>The assignment of port number 4647 is strongly suggested (DOTS
        signal channel uses port number 4646).</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="map" title="DOTS Signal Channel CBOR Mappings Registry">
        <t>This specification registers the 'source-prefix' and
        'source-port-range' parameters in the IANA "DOTS Signal Channel CBOR
        Mappings" registry established by <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The source-prefix and source-port-range are comprehension-optional
        parameters.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[+-------------------+-------------+---------+---------------+--------+
| Parameter Name    | YANG        | CBOR    | CBOR Major    | JSON   |
|                   | Type        | Key     |    Type &     | Type   |
|                   |             |         | Information   |        |
+-------------------+-------------+---------+---------------+--------+
| source-prefix     | leaf-list   |   0x8000| 4 array       | Array  |
|                   | inet:       |   (TBD) |               |        |
|                   |  ip-prefix  |         | 3 text string | String |
| source-port-range | list        |   0x8001| 4 array       | Array  |
|                   |             |   (TBD) |               |        | 
+-------------------+-------------+---------+---------------+--------+

    Table 4: CBOR Mappings Used in DOTS Signal Channel Messages]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="yang" title="DOTS Signal Channel YANG Module">
        <t>This document requests IANA to register the following URIs in the
        "IETF XML Registry" <xref target="RFC3688"></xref>: <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[         URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-dots-signal-call-home
         Registrant Contact: The IESG.
         XML: N/A; the requested URI is an XML namespace.

         URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-dots-data-call-home
         Registrant Contact: The IESG.
         XML: N/A; the requested URI is an XML namespace.
]]></artwork>
          </figure> This document requests IANA to register the following YANG
        modules in the "YANG Module Names" registry <xref
        target="RFC7950"></xref>.<figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[         name: ietf-signal-call-home
         namespace: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-dots-signal-call-home
         prefix: signal-call-home
         reference: RFC XXXX

         name: ietf-data-call-home
         namespace: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-dots-data-call-home
         prefix: data-call-home
         reference: RFC XXXX
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document deviates from standard DOTS signal channel usage by
      having the DOTS server initiate the TCP/TLS or DTLS connection. DOTS
      signal channel related security considerations discussed in Section 10
      of <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel"></xref> MUST be
      considered. DOTS agents MUST authenticate each other using (D)TLS before
      a DOTS signal channel session is considered valid.</t>

      <t>An attacker may launch a DoS attack on the DOTS client by having it
      perform computationally expensive operations, before deducing that the
      attacker doesn't possess a valid key. For instance, in TLS 1.3 <xref
      target="RFC8446"></xref>, the ServerHello message contains a Key Share
      value based on an expensive asymmetric key operation for key
      establishment. Common precautions mitigating DoS attacks are
      recommended, such as temporarily blacklisting the source address after a
      set number of unsuccessful authentication attempts.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>TBC.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dots-data-channel" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7252"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7950"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3688"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8446"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8071'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel" ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4732"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7049"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4632"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8071"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4960"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4340"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5575"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dots-requirements"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-dots-use-cases'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
